You're welcome.
And can I just say
thank you very much for bearing with us.
I know that we've mulled you around repeatedly.
It has not been within our
power. It's been because the house has gone to extended hours, et cetera.
So it's been frustrating for us, but I know it's been frustrating for you, so thank
you. So we really appreciate it.
We are basically right up towards the end of our hearing part of it,
part of the ports inquiry. But we
really appreciate having you here because without that, there'll be a substantial
gap in our knowledge. So
what I thought I'd do is hand over to you for if you want to make some introductory
remarks.
Yep.
And then there will be plenty of questions. I know I've got a long line up.
Simon knows that I ask lots of questions.
Just given the questions on the RMA, so
replacement, should I say?
Yeah.
Okay. But in your hands, Leon.
Look, thank you very much.
I don't know how much you know about MSC, but we're a-
Tell us a bit anyway. Yeah
Yeah, will do. We're a family-owned international shipping
company,
started in 1970 by Mr. Aponte with one ship,
and grown since then to be the largest container carrier in the world.
Also the largest privately owned
cruise operator in the world as well, as well as one of the largest port
operators and one of the largest cargo operators in the world.
So quite a success story from a global footprint perspective.
Within New Zealand, we started off with one person working out of his
laundry in Auckland in 1996. We celebrated
30 years in New Zealand last month-
Nice
... in June. So thank you very much.
All right. Good then.
Really a great milestone achievement for us.
Nice function that we had in Christchurch, where our head office is, with our team.
We have 76 people in the country, so a fairly large
local footprint. And then
we have a number of people that support the business across in Fremantle,
which is our head office for the region today.
So when we started off as MSC in New Zealand,
we basically slot charted on board a vessel that was going across from
here to
Australia,
and New Zealand was connected through Australia to the rest of the world.
Today, we operate our own three dedicated services in New
Zealand.
Our flagship service being the Eagle, which we launched in February
this year.
That's a direct link between New Zealand and the USA, and then
connecting from Panama into the world as well.
Mostly focused around Europe and Africa and the Med.
Then we have the Southern Loop, which is a service that comes out of Melbourne and
does the south up and connects into Wellington to feed into the Eagle,
and also across into Australia, to connect to the world as well
from there.
And then we have the Noumea Express, which it's all in the name, goes through
Noumea and the islands, comes into Tauranga, and then goes back to Australia from
there and does a loop. So that's essentially us in
a nutshell in terms of where we've come from.
We're very much interested in growing in New Zealand.
We have grown this year,
with double-digit growth for us-
Awesome
... across the board.
Particularly in Wellington, we've partnered very closely with Centreport
this year, where we've actually seen a 350% increase
in our throughput through Wellington,
starting from February this year with the introduction of our Eagle service.
So Wellington is our hub that we operate with today,
and our services connect from the rest of the country into Wellington and then
load onto either the Southern Loop or the
Eagle going deep sea from here.
Cool.
That's it.
Thank you very much. That's good to get that.
And we will also get a Hansard, so we've got all those
routes in particular because I'm not-- Let's kick ourselves off with
questions. So Dan and then I'll take one.
Thanks, Mr. Chair. Thanks, Leon. I appreciate you coming in again.
Sorry for the delay in-
No problem
...
meeting with you. Just reading through your submission, you've got, I think, a
pretty good articulation of some of the key issues in the sector.
Yep.
How do we power up productivity?
If we were to say to you,
"What's the top three things that you want as a result of this
inquiry
for us to improve productivity of the sector?" And before I hand it over to
you, just-
Yeah
... some of the previous submissions have talked about kind of encouraging more of
a hub and spoke model-
Mm-hmm
... across the sector.
We've talked about
getting more accurate data and measurement on productivity
measures across port boards.
There's been discussions about section, is it 98 of the-
198.
Yeah.
So that has been an impediment to-
That's all
... productivity-
Mm-hmm
... from overseas operators.
Mm-hmm.
That just gives you a flavor, but
hand it over to you, what do you think we should be looking at from
a government recommendations perspective on how they
can improve productivity?
Yeah. Okay. Thank you. And thanks for the background.
I did watch some of the feeds before, so I've had a little bit of insight into the
conversations.
Our belief is that there's not a one-size-fits-all
solution to the challenge because actually, the
dynamic footprint of New Zealand, the geographical footprint, and the
challenges that come with that, represents particular challenges in each of the
different ports.
So I don't think there's a silver bullet that we can put out there and say, "If you
do this one thing or these three things, that'll solve all of the challenges."
I think each port has its own constraints, and each port needs to grapple with
that and figure out ways to be able to handle that challenge.
We operate with both a hub and spoke and a direct mechanism
today. So essentially, the evil is our hub and spoke, and we
use Wellington as our hub for that service.
But then the Southern Group is also a direct option going from the likes of Bluff
directly into Australia as well. So we have a bit of
a hybrid
policy. Globally, MSC is--
We focus very much on standalone services and
creating direct optionality for our customers.
We have a little bit of a benefit in terms of we're over 1,000 container ships.
So being 21, I think it's 21.5% of the global container
market and having the world's largest fleet allows us to be a little bit
more dynamic in that port-to-port pairing.
What we find with the hub and spoke mechanism is that it's really good to connect
the smaller ports into a larger system for the
deep sea leg. It does add cost to the system, though, because it's extra
handling that comes into it. And depending on where you are on that leg
of the pre-feeder service, it can add quite a lot of
transit time onto your cargo. So it could be ten days around the New Zealand coast,
plus potentially when that connecting vessel connects into the hub, another week
as you wait for the weekly service to come through, depending on your connections
hub. Now, part of the challenge as a carrier is when we
look at these system designs that we've put in place, we try and limit
those connection gaps as much as possible.
We need to give the port some time to be able to resource up and manage
the flows of the cargo. But you don't want to try and have a
vessel arriving on a Monday to connect on a vessel that
departed on a Sunday. You want to try and have it arrive on a Sunday to connect to
the vessel arrive on the Monday instead.
The challenge that we have in New Zealand ports now is because of the challenges
we've seen over the last sort of four to five years, there is no flexibility.
So all of the ports, or 90% of the ports are oversubscribed.
There's not that ability as a carrier to sit there and go, "I'd like a Wednesday
window in this port, followed by a Friday window in that port," because it connects
in the most efficient manner possible.
So what we end up seeing, and you can have a look at that on some of our routings,
we actually have a bit of a higgledy-piggledy where we backtrack because we can't
get a berth in that port. So we've got to go to the next port, come back to that
port, load the cargo, and then go to the next port from there.
So creating a little bit of space in the
terminals is paramount for us.
It's a bit of a crude saying, but shipping happens.
We have a lot of delays, especially around the New Zealand coast, especially this
time of the year. And in order for us to recover, our
optionality is very limited in New Zealand today.
We have the potential to be able to speed up the vessels, but we have to
be conscious of emissions. So by significantly increasing
that, you also increase emissions and you also increase cost that comes with
that. So having that little bit of play
within the ports to be able to say, "Well, yes, I'm late, but I'm only three hours
late," as opposed to if you arrive late, you can't have a berth.
The next vessel's waiting for the berth, and you wait a week for that berth.
So what you see happening today is carriers are doing a lot of omissions,
ourselves included.
Or we call it a COR, change of rotation, where instead of doing the most
efficient route on a planned voyage, we change the route to
be able to call the next port so we don't lose that berth as well because of the
cascading impact.
So
to me, it's about trying to find, for each one of those particular
ports, what is the limiting factor around their
productivity
and how do we address that? How do we help them? Is it CapEx?
Is it
access to labor? Is it whatever might be the challenge
that's creating that particular hub to or that particular port
to have the constraints that it has.
And then also, there's a little bit of capacity around the coast that's not
necessarily fully utilized today.
And that's the reason why we partnered with Centreport, because they had
quite a lot of capacity that was underutilized post the earthquake.
And we've seen them gear up quite substantially.
I mentioned it earlier on,
from February to May this year versus February to May the year before, we've
increased by 350% our volumes coming through here.
So from 8,000 containers to 38,000 containers
hubbing through the port here, and that was capacity they had. They have invested.
They put, I think, around about $15 million in, in terms of
new reefer towers and employed 50 new
staff to be able to manage the volume throughput.
But they had the footprint, they had the capacity to be able to grow
and the want and the commercial nous to be able to do that.
So that to me is an example of where we can do that in a safe
environment, in a productive environment as well.
Excellent. So just
take from that answer, definitely optimizing and
providing the flexibility within each port around
docking and coming in and going. That's
one.
Yep.
The second thing I take from what you've just said is more of a port-by-port
specific analysis on what's the limiting
constraint.
Yeah.
So that's something that government can
do is sort of port by port.
Just rounding it off in terms of next cab off the rank or a
third area that you think we need to be looking in?
It's something I've
thought is missing for a while, and you can probably tell by my accent that
I've got a bit of a different view on the outside world, if I can put it
that way.
Is that sort of that
long-term thinking that centralized,
disconnected from any political cycles, disconnected from any local
drivers that might be the case that actually drive the infrastructure network for
New Zealand that is thinking of NZ Inc and driving
a uniformed approach where- We don't have unnecessary
spend taking place in certain places, under-investment taking place in other
areas, and a sort of shared view so that we as
industry can actually invest and know that's the 30-year plan
because we're talking 30, 50-year investments that we need to make to be
able to make it work. Right now, the way that we're doing is we're
dealing with each port individually and we're trying to
sort of make our own assumptions as to what that future-
Yeah
...
prospect looks like.
Good. Thank you.
Mr. Chair.
Thank you. Yeah, okay, Simon. We can begin.
How much of that constraint around
port efficiency or the
flow of freight is down to connections to and
from the ports, land connections
to landside infrastructure and land ports and so on?
Because around New Zealand, we've got different rail and road
configurations. When you look at Auckland, you come off the bottom of Stanley
Street there, you drive a truck and trailer, and you end up in what
appears to be a 19th century kind of bullet track, like winding your way
around the waterfront.
Yeah.
Then you've got to navigate cyclists who always have priority in New Zealand.
Whereas I would've thought if we wanted a well-functioning link to the
rest of the transport network, you might want a dedicated
tunnel or something straight into the port for your heavies.
So, how much of that is a constraint?
Yeah, look, I think it's a very fair point.
Scalability really comes off the back of rail,
and being able to connect those nodes.
We can see the proof point in the Metroport and Tauranga development.
That's really performed well. There's been a significant change there now, which
is, in my opinion, performed better.
So, that's a great example of how rail can
enable those connections. There are some parts of the country where that doesn't
make sense, and that's where having the blue corridor,
the coastal connection, makes a lot of sense.
We've been serving Bluff pretty much from day one.
We're the only container carrier that calls into Bluff, and that's a great example
of very heavy cargo. You've got the Rio Tinto
coming out of there and other produce from the area that it
doesn't really make sense to try and haul that across anywhere.
So, having a dedicated product that's there week in, week out
enables that industry. So again, it's a little bit of a hybrid.
But 100% agree, there's a stranglehold
going into and out of the various nodes that we have today, for sure.
So the committee was going to take away
something to feed back into the infrastructure
system. It's making sure that the right investments are made in that
connecting infrastructure,
and sources for courses, but you're going to get the best bang for buck
by building your rail capacity into ports-
Completely agree
... to move the most boxes in the shortest possible amount of time.
Completely agree, and I'd add it to that third point that I made in terms of having
that centralized direction, centralized thought pattern because
we see a number of ICDs today, inland container depots today,
where you might have one port-
Sorry, just tell us what's an ICD.
Inland container depot.
Right.
So that's what you're talking about now, having that rail corridor.
Yeah.
So having the
container closer to the customer, they don't have a very long road leg.
They can truck into the depot,
get it empty, take it to their pack plant, pack it, put it back into the depot, and
rail it into the port, or have a land bridge as well, like
a truck leg.
So what we see that has happened in the past is not happening necessarily too much
today, but what has happened in the past is you've had different ports having
similar ideas and building their own ICDs next door to each other.
There's only so much capital in New Zealand.
Right.
We need to think a little bit smarter and pool that resource.
And how do we actually take that and go, "Well, actually, let's have it
disconnected from the ports. Let's have a third party, whatever that might be, that
operates that." It could be a port that operates it.
It doesn't really make a difference.
But instead of you investing $300 million and me investing $300
million, let's invest $450 million and save $150 million,
and have a shared facility that serves everybody in that community, and
all the
both importers and exporters that come through there.
So, that's kind of where I say that that third point really stacks up in
terms of being able to give us that 30-year, 50-year plan around how do we
actually make the smart investments in the country?
Oh, okay.
So
we could, let's say we go down that 30-year plan arrangement.
We manage to persuade the ports to be involved in that way or require the
ports to be involved in that way.
What is the certainty we've got that we know what you're doing and what the other
shipping lines are doing which actually works in with that, as opposed to saying,
"Well, we've just decided that you put all this infrastructure in," let's say out
of Auckland, "We've decided we're going out of Tauranga instead because somehow
we've got a better deal for it." What's to
make sure that all the parts of the system are working together well?
Look, I can't talk for the other carriers.
I can only talk for-
No, let's just talk to your own arrangements
... But, we will go where the cargo is.
That's as simple as that. That's our business. That's what we focus on.
We move international freight. So if the cargo is in a centralized
hub, we'll go to a centralized hub.
If the cargo is in a diversified hub, we'll go to a diversified hub.
So that's why I said earlier on today, we run a hybrid model where we have a hub
and spoke, and we also have a direct
port pay connect that we have in place because
it's that diverse today within New Zealand.
So,
there's other ways of doing it as well.
I mentioned earlier on that we have other parts of our business as well, and other
carriers have other parts of their business as well.
I think we're top three or top five port operators in the world today
as TIL, which is a part of our business.
And so there's potential investment opportunities on that front as well.
But to me, at the end of the day, it comes down to where the cargo is.
If the cargo is moved into specifically an efficient
hub that we can get a vessel in and get it out as quickly as possible,
we'd go there.
So when we talk about hub and spoke-
Mm-hmm
... one of the interesting things is which ports you actually, as shipping
lines, which ports you actually go to.
One of the things we've had impressed on us is that the vessels are going to get
larger. Some ports are not going to be able to cope with those, so that kind of
cuts them out of being a place that those vessels can go to, because they simply
physically can't accommodate them.
Hmm.
But which ports do you end up-- You could make a decision.
The one example we've had in particular is in the South Island, where
Lyttelton appears to have aspirations to take the business out of Timaru
and Port Otago.
Mm-hmm.
So who's getting to decide? Is it the freight
provider, whether it's
Fonterra or
Kotahi? Are they going to decide which port it's going out of?
Are you going to decide? Are the ports going to compete amongst each other on
price? How does that work? Because there are, as you indicated,
some really significant investment proposals-
Yes
... which
may be good investments or may be not very good investments.
Yeah.
I guess I'll answer that in a couple of phases.
To answer your core question in terms of who makes that decision, at the end of the
day, it's the shipper and the importer.
So if a large importer goes and builds a deconsolidation
facility in Palmerston North,
the cargo will move to Palmerston North,
and they'll distribute from there.
If they build a major hub in
Lyttelton to support the plan that
Lyttelton has, then the cargo will move there, and they'd be
responsible for that.
So just to pick that one up. So if Lyttelton were to build, I'm using this as an
example, if they were to build a hub, that's a port making an investment decision.
Mm-hmm.
Are you saying that that would necessarily derive a Kotahi, for
example? So I'm going to take the produce out of Southland and send it through
Lyttelton as opposed to-
Mm-hmm
... through South Port or-
No, the shipper makes the decision at the end of it.
That's what I want to understand. Yeah
The shipper makes the decision. So if the shipper is driving it, the shipper would
have to be a part of that. So you say Kotahi, so Fonterra or Silver Fern Farms-
Yeah
... in conjunction with Kotahi and the other customers would then say, okay, as
part of that project, I would imagine that those discussions would be
made before putting a billion dollars in the ground.
And that's the point, yeah.
Yes.
Yeah, okay.
But you have to have the cargo there because otherwise you're holding a white
elephant.
Yep. Indeed.
In terms of the question around the vessels getting larger,
I think we need to put that into context.
Globally, vessels are definitely getting larger.
24,000, 25,000 TEU ships
on the East-West trades are commonplace today.
And up until probably October last year, the new
builds were 80%-plus weighted on 12,000
TEU and larger vessels. There's been a bit of a
shift since then. So BIMCO released their latest
report in February this year. They haven't updated it yet.
But they estimate that below 12,000 TEU ships have
significantly ramped up in the new orders
to the extent of about 33% of the new builds been in
that 8,000 and below TEU
capacity vessels. So there are new, smaller ships being built,
and that's because not every port is ever going to-- Some ports have granite
bottoms. They can't get down to 12, 14, and 16-meter drafts.
And those ports still have to be served.
We still need to be able to connect into those hubs with the spokes.
So there will still be vessels. There just won't be
as many of them,
and they won't be as efficient as a 24,000 TEU
vessel once it's on the water. But
when a 24,000 TEU vessel's alongside and you've got to load 10,000
TEU on board that vessel in two days,
that takes up a lot of resource, and that takes up a lot of capital to be able
to get to that stage.
So what you're saying is, is what you're saying that you will continue to service
New Zealand with vessels which are appropriate size for the
ports that you're going to?
Correct.
Yeah, okay. Right. Cool.
Other questions before I go onto another area?
Okay. Look, can I just ask you about the issue of windows?
Yes.
And that is, we regularly get the-- I'd be interested in, first of all, in your
observations about how on time your own vessels are.
Mm-hmm.
But also what happens when they get to New Zealand, what the flexibility is in the
system. You mentioned the IMO and being able to speed up, et cetera.
My understanding is that we have not yet, or our understanding is that we have not
yet signed the IMO agreement.
Correct. Yes.
And that looks parked because I don't think we're the only ones unhappy with it.
But the ability to be able to get vessels on time
in and out-
Yeah
... flexibility to be able to deal with those
will be really helpful. And also how different ports deal
with windows with vessels that arrive out of window, because I know
Napier told me when I visited them, they said, "You got Wednesday.
You miss Wednesday this week, it's Wednesday next week."
Yes.
That's an interesting way of doing it, as opposed to, well, we'll take you when we
can.
Yes.
So I'd be interested in your observations on that.
Yeah, look, there's a lot to that question.
So in terms of our schedule reliability, we actually recently made a
change to our network because we weren't happy with the reliability
on our previous service, the Wallaby-
Mm-hmm
... and moved to the Southern Loop.
And by doing that, we disconnected some of the more challenging areas.
We found that the vessels were late coming out of China quite often.
And then that's where the regulation kicks in, where we can't speed up
deep sea.
Within New Zealand, if we need to, we do.
But that obviously comes at a significant cost and environmental impact that we
bear in mind as well.
So there's definitely a challenge with vessels getting into
the country on time. No
country in the world today, I would hazard to guess, is
100% on time all the time.
So it's 100%, yeah.
Yeah.
I can't remember the exact number, but global schedule reliability is in the
mid-60s, mid to high 60s.
That's global.
That's global schedule reliability.
Okay.
It's not a-
And specific to New Zealand, it's a global challenge
that's
ongoing with the
geopolitical challenges that we see and having to navigate that,
and also the volume growth that we've seen.
So
there's definitely challenges getting into the country on time.
That said, even when we do get in on time, we still leave late,
and that's for a number of reasons.
Worse than you. So is the reliability worse when you leave than it was when you got
here?
Yes.
Yeah.
So in our submission, we made the statement, and this is
going back a number of years, but New Zealand used to
be a country where we would be able to come in slightly delayed, not
badly delayed, but recover that schedule around the coast because in
2015, we were a lot more productive
per crane and per vessel birth rate than what we
are today.
So
you add to that the volume increase between 2015
and today, which is basis the FIG stats,
which are only available up until March, so I only have quarter one
data. But if you look at that versus 2015, same
12-month window, it's about 200,000 containers extra that we're doing
at a lower productivity, which equates to 30% longer for ships
being alongside in New Zealand. So that soaks up all of that flex that we had in
the
ports before, because no port would be efficient or would be
a healthy business if they had 30-plus percent unused
capacity at any given time.
Mm.
5%, 10% makes a lot of sense, and you can flex between them.
You can actually use that capacity to recover delays and
maybe you have additional project cargo or spot business or those kinds of things,
then you can look at those opportunities,
but that's just not there.
So what specifically has happened as far as you're aware that's reduced-- Because
you're basically saying that we are less productive now-
Yeah
... per container move, crane hour, whatever, than we were a decade ago.
Yeah.
What's changed?
Just the overall productivity in the ports has changed.
Could you-
And the volume has also lifted.
Right, and the volume's-
The volume's also lifted. So if we go 2015 to today, it's about
200,000 containers extra basis the FIG stats using the figs.
But are you saying that a crane today lifts less?
Yes.
Why? Do you know?
Like I said earlier on, it's specific to each port that they have their
constraints within it that drive the reasoning behind that.
It might be that some-
Mm
... ports have aging infrastructure, aging cranes that
need a little bit more downtime, need a little bit of care.
It might be that some ports have struggled to resource
the landside to feed the crane. Some might be a resourcing issue for the
crane itself. There's multiple different
reasons for each port, and I think
if you speak to the ports, they would understand that for each of their ports
specifically, or they should. The conversations we have with them, they definitely
do.
Hmm. That's concerning to hear that particular...
But
anybody else got other questions for him?
No.
Or I carry on? Section 198-
Yeah
... you mentioned.
Yep.
Can you tell us about that? SWIs kind of made life a little bit easier in some
ways, and since they decided they can't make it work at the moment.
But the optimal way in which you've already said you do some doubling back, but at
the moment you're constrained in what you can do.
What would the ideal arrangement be for you?
In terms of Section 198,
from a MSC perspective, we see our core task as
international freight-
Mm
... not coastal freight.
Coastal freight is incidental
as to the journey that we're underway with.
And that's not because that's what it says in the act. That's really what we do.
We're not a coastal operator.
If it helps our customers, and they need a hand-
Mm
... like us being the only carrier that goes into Bluff,
we do help customers on that as part of the leg, but it's
not something we actively market or something we actively sell.
So I wouldn't be sitting here today saying to you that fundamentally
changing the act is going to make a major difference in the way that we
serve this market. I think there are certain carriers where it
makes a lot of sense, and how those nodes connect, and for
certain customers, it makes a lot of sense that they might have to
consolidate or move ingredients from one part of
the country to another part of the country for manufacturing.
And the efficiencies that would be driven by that would make a lot of sense for
them. Using the same container, unpack a coastal
box, clean it out, and pack it with exports makes a lot of sense
in that regard for sure.
Yeah. So going back to the issue of vessels getting
back on time, what can be done to improve that?
And related to that, you basically said that there's a lack of capacity in the
system. One of the things that sort of come through at the moment is obviously
there's no regulation at the moment about the port charges.
And I have actually either spent a day with the Port of Auckland the other day,
which was great.
But
basically, they said that the limiting
of the port charge effectively is the equivalent cost of the land transport to the
next possible port that somebody might-
Correct. Yes
... might use.
If there were to be some form of Commerce Commission
oversight, transparency,
et cetera, involved there,
you would, by the sounds of things being say, that there would need to be
some factoring in of you actually need some surplus capacity.
You can't take it right down to the wire because that's going to cause some
significant issues.
Yeah. I would-
And that capacity would then have to be paid for in that system.
Yeah. I would think so.
I think if you look at it in terms of the natural cargo capture for ports,
right?
Napier's a great example. So a large percentage,
70-plus percent of their cargo is within 20 kilometers of the port.
Whereas centre port is not the case.
They have to pull cargo from all over the country.
So if you have a one-size-fits-all model, you'd handicap one and
benefit the other with that system being the case, right?
And so the comment around it only costs as much as what-- Or we can only
increase the rates as much as what it costs to get to the next port is
essentially that sort of metric that's there, right?
So yes, I think
if you can manage that, and I'll make no bones
about it, the significant cost increases that we've seen is a contributing factor
towards the challenges that we see in New
Zealand today. I did some really brief numbers before I came in.
If you look at
the CPI increase from 2015 to today, it's around about
36% compound interest over that period of time, the increase.
And we're sitting above 50% in terms of actual cost increase in
port handling itself.
So port handling charges up over 50%?
Yes.
Yeah.
So, and that's just what's been advertised out to the
market using publicly available data, right?
Yeah.
And so you add to that then the challenges that we
have around the coast with those contingencies that I spoke about and a significant
increase in cost in able to, being able to, if you do a change of rotation,
we're talking hundreds of thousands of dollars in terms of the amount of fuel
that we're using. If we do an omission, we have to pay for storage of those
containers in the port because it's not the customer's fault that we had to omit.
It's our decision that we made. Might be weather, might be whatever might
be the case, but we can't go to a shipper and say to them, "We decided to omit the
port. You need to pay them for the privilege of holding your cargo for a week's
delay." Right? So all those costs all add up, and then you
add a significant cost to serve on top of that sort of base cost.
It becomes a very difficult market to serve.
So bearing in mind that if you create more capacity, and
bearing in mind the comment you've already made about the efficiency of the
ports handling having overall declined,
are you better off or is the system, because, I mean, your
charges get imposed on the
cargo owners,
ultimately anyway.
Would the cargo owners be better off if you actually have that extra capacity,
which will cost something, than they would be at the moment with
delays, out of window,
potentially having to bypass ports occasionally because you can't get a
window and so on?
Bless you.
I would say so,
especially in the long run. So short term,
there'd probably be a cost impact that came with that.
But if you look at that 30-year horizon that we spoke about,
the challenge that we have today is it's a today problem.
I mean, we can't bring a new service into Tauranga today because they don't
have the space on the berth to be able to put a new service on.
So that limits our ability, and that's for all carriers, right?
It limits our ability to give options to shippers.
If the government's serious about the
export growth that's expected,
yes, definitely, it's a must.
Yeah. Okay. I think
I'm going to carry on as well while the other-- You know, because nobody else has
got questions at the moment.
I think you've kind of intimated you are committed to New Zealand
long term. Yep, cool. Right.
The choice of ports served, that is a decision you make on the
basis of what the customers, the cargo owners-
Exactly
... have decided. Okay, that's fine.
Just the issue of balancing container traffic, movement of
containers.
Mm-hmm.
Can you just give us a bit of
your insight into that? Because from what we understand is,
well, reefers, in particular, tend to be out-
Yes
... go out full. There's not a lot of demand for them coming back
full. But also the movement of containers around the
system. Obviously, a lot of empties turn up various
different places, and then they've got to-- They occupy space
on boards, in ships-
Mm-hmm
... on railway wagons, et cetera, being moved around the country.
Have we got that optimally ar-- What does it look like if we got that optimally
arranged?
Again, talking for my own business, I would say no,
in terms of
it being optimal. New Zealand, if you look at it
purely on an import-export basis using the figs stats looks
relatively well-balanced, in terms of volumes. It ebbs and flows.
Imports are a little bit down because the economy hasn't recovered as well as
expected. That will grow. Exports are doing really well, so it's
slightly imbalanced now, but total number-
Number of containers
... number of containers-
Yep
... roughly there or thereabouts.
It's when you drop down into the equipment size types
that it gets really interesting. So the imports are really
predominantly 40-foot high cube imports.
Your widgets, your
barbecues, your
fridges, and the likes coming in.
There's a bit of commodity import coming in in 20s.
And then your exports are predominantly,
we do move a lot of 40 foots out, but not the same amount.
Our dynamic, we move a lot of 20 foots out of New Zealand.
And these are refrigerated?
No. Well, we do a lot of refrigerated 20 foots as well
out of New Zealand, but dry containers as well.
So we have an imbalance on 20-foot dryers as well as
reefer containers. And that's serving the wine market really.
There's a lot of wine that moves heavy boxes in
20 foots, and we need specific containers for that, with the bladders and
everything else that goes into in the inside of the container.
So
in terms of the actual size types,
20-foot reefer, 40-foot reefer are very imbalanced in
that we don't import nearly as much as what we export, so we bring them in
empty. And- 20-foot dry is
imbalanced. We don't import as many as what we export,
and 40-foot is imbalanced the other way around, 40-foot dry, where we
import more than what we export. So
it's not efficient.
Okay. And when you've
got these containers on the ship, it doesn't matter whether it's empty or
whether it's full, you're charging the same effectively?
Well, I mean-
Oh, no
... no difference reefer-wise versus not?
No, it makes a massive difference.
Does it? Okay.
Makes a massive difference. So we don't charge for-- There's no invoice that goes
out for an empty to come into the country.
It's built into the freight for either the import or the export.
If it's an empty that's imported, it's built into the total cost of the export.
But there's no actual invoice that gets sent to a customer saying, "I repositioned
this container in from Shenzhen, and you need to pay me
$500 for that." That's not the case.
Okay.
Where the difference comes in is in terms of the stowage on board the
vessel, managing the
GM of the ship or the balance of the vessel.
Yeah.
If you have to carry a whole lot of empties around the coast
and you want to load fulls at the first port, it becomes
you can't put heavy boxes on top of light boxes.
You have a weight issue on board the ship.
So stability issues, all those kinds of things come into it.
So you end up having to do restows, take the empty off, load the
full, put the empty back on. So that then creates more inefficiencies in the
port and creates more cost to the system as well.
So effectively what you're saying, there's no specific charge, but there is a-
It's a sunk cost
... built into the cost of-
Yes
... the export in the first place. So how can we make it more efficient?
Because there's a lot of movements there.
Yeah. I mentioned it a little bit earlier on,
where there's
opportunities for being able to link up imports and exports,
reuse of containers.
If you have those centralized facilities, that becomes a lot
more possible. So you're not moving a container
from
Wellington to Whanganui and back to Wellington again.
You can repack it and then when moving it back there because a subsequent booking
was made for a full. If you could connect up those nodes and say, well, we've got
full exports out of this region, we can reuse those containers for those full
exports. That makes it a lot more efficient.
Sure.
And so you can connect it up a lot more with visibility of data.
Got it. So it's very much how we manage the inland
side of things that will make the difference in that area. Okay.
And data visibility. I mentioned it earlier on.
We're using the FIG stats today and end of July and
the latest information, or sorry, I did it the day before yesterday, so the latest
information then was the end of March.
And that information's not complete either because we don't
have all the ports submitting information to that.
So not having data visibility, not being able to
use the most recent information, and that data on its
own is very poor data. There's not a lot that you can read
into the information that comes through that.
Whereas if you look at some of the other countries in the world where there's
aggregated stats around destination markets, around origins,
around all those size types and everything else that comes with that,
it gives you a lot more certainty around driving decisions
and having those conversations.
So, and then I'll go to Julie-Anne in just a sec. So you got one too, Dave?
No.
Okay. So the data that you're talking about, I just had a meeting with Port
Connect-
Yep
... very recently. They said you at the moment are not involved with that
particular proposition, which is
about the ships themselves and where they are rather than
how they unload, et cetera.
But you're saying that the data you're looking for there is essentially the
volumes of containers,
where they are, where they need to go, all of those sort of things.
You're saying that data is not particularly good at the moment?
It doesn't exist.
Having centralized data-
So who should govern that?
That should be a third party, definitely not one of the carriers, and definitely
not one of the ports, and not one of the key stakeholders in that process, for
sure. And it should be aggregated as well, right?
Yeah.
So it shouldn't be a competitive advantage for anybody. Let's put it that way.
But the point that I'm trying to make is that we have no market
data today. I mean, the last freight study, I don't know, it's maybe 10 years ago,
eight years ago.
And we're still busy building plans and executing on strategies based as
that. So we don't actually have anything that's sort of gone,
were those assumptions correct? I know there's a plan in place to address that now.
But
we're kind of flying blind in terms of an industry making decisions.
That's very helpful, and it's one of the kind of areas that what I think we will
certainly give thought to as to-
Mm.
We want to be a little bit more farsighted about this.
Julie-Anne.
Yeah. Thank you so much, Sven. Very interesting.
I kind of wanted to go back to that tension between
domestic coastal shipping and international.
And just wondered if you had any thoughts, because
we
potentially could have
some economic advantage domestically by
supporting a domestic coastal operation to be as an
alternative to rail and road.
Mm-hmm.
But to get it to that point, it's very difficult for it to work for
various reasons, but one is the competition with international
shipping, which is able to do it cheaper.
Some of the concerns are around
labor standards on foreign flag vessels and
stuff like that.
Mm-hmm.
I was just wondering, I think for New Zealand Inc, it makes sense to
have both
operating.
But policy-wise, it is difficult to see how to
get there.
I don't know if you have any thoughts on-
Yeah. I'm by no means an authority on coastal shipping.
Yeah.
I think the guys at Pacific could probably share a few runs on the board that
they've had, the challenges that they've faced.
Yeah.
And my sort of two cents, using my knowledge base on it,
is that probably one of the constricting factors for coastal
shipping is similar to the constricting factors that we have in international
shipping, in that we can't get a ship through the port fast enough.
Yeah.
And especially on coastal, they have a lot of name-day
deliveries-
Mm, sure
... so they need to be there for that supply chain to work every Wednesday,
and they need to be in this port every Friday for that supply chain to work as
efficiently for their major customers.
And not being able to berth on a particular
day has a significant ramification for
their business and for their customers.
So,
we operate under move count restrictions-
Mm
... in a number of ports today.
And what that means is we get given a window, and port calculates, it
bases our productivity. In those 12 hours, we can do 1,000
containers, as an example. So we can't do more than 1,000 moves.
Sometimes there's a bit of flex, depending on the ports.
But within that space, your number one priority is you need to get the containers
off the ship.
Mm.
Then you want to load your deep sea exports, and you might need to position
out some equipment because of that imbalance that you have.
So only after those sort of first three priorities does coastal
become a option for us.
So it's not that it's not important to us, it's
just that that's not our core-
Yeah
... what our purpose is.
Yeah.
Okay.
Look, I think we are at time, so I
thank you very much for what you've added.
You've certainly added a few elements that we hadn't had before, and I think that's
very helpful. And we had heard from Maersk before.
We heard from Swire before as well, but I'd like to have you here
from a shipping perspective, I think is very helpful.
So
thank you very much.
Thanks very much.
My pleasure.
And thank you for bearing with us. Thank you.